<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [

<!ENTITY RFC1958 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1958.xml">
]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-iab-internet-consolidation-00" ipr="trust200902">

  <front>

    <title abbrev="Low Latency">Considerations on Internet Consolidation and the Internet Architecture</title>

    <author fullname="Jari Arkko" initials="J." 
            surname="Arkko">
      <organization>Ericsson</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city>Kauniainen</city>

          <region></region>

          <code>02700</code>

          <country>Finland</country>
        </postal>

        <email>jari.arkko@piuha.net</email>

      </address>
    </author>
    
    <author fullname="Brian Trammell" initials="B." surname="Trammell">
      <organization>...</organization>
      <address>
        <email>ietf@trammell.ch</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    
    <author fullname="Mark Nottingham" initials="M." surname="Nottingham">
      <organization>...</organization>
      <address>
        <email>mnot@mnot.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    
    <author fullname="Christian Huitema" initials="C." surname="Huitema">
      <organization>...</organization>
      <address>
        <email>...</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    
    <author fullname="Martin Thomson" initials="M." surname="Thomson">
      <organization>...</organization>
      <address>
        <email>...</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    
    <author fullname="Jeff Tantsura" initials="J." surname="Tantsura">
      <organization>Futurewei, Future Networks</organization>
      <address>
        <email>jefftant.ietf@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="May" year="2018" />

    <area>Internet</area>

    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>

    <abstract>

      <t>Is Internet traffic consolidating, i.e., moving towards a
      larger fraction of traffic involving a small set of large
      content providers, social networks, and content delivery
      platforms? It certainly appears so, though more research on this
      topic would be welcome. But what might this mean for the
      Internet? And are our technology and architecture choices
      affecting some of these trends? Would different technology
      change the trends in some fashion?</t>

    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>

    <section title="Introduction">

      <t>One of the tasks of the Internet Architecture Board is to
      look at trends affecting the Internet. Recently, we've been
      discussing traffic flows and popular applications on the
      Internet, and the role of smaller vs. larger players in the
      Internet ecosystem.</t>

      <t>Is Internet traffic consolidating, i.e., moving towards a
      larger fraction of traffic involving a small set of large
      content providers, social networks, and content delivery
      platforms? It certainly appears so, though more research on this
      topic would be welcome. But what might this mean for the
      Internet? And are our technology and architecture choices
      affecting some of these trends? Would different technology
      change the trends in some fashion?</t>


      <t>The IAB's remit is to focus on technology, but of course we
      also want to invite input on the implications and externalities
      of those arrangements. Technology affects economics and vice
      versa. The Internet technology community continues to make
      decisions that have ramifications on Internet systems, just as
      we are subject to forces that affect them: the consolidation
      trend also raises relevant and interesting technical and
      architectural questions. </t>

      <t>For instance, a year ago we talked about large-scale
      denial-of-service attacks, and how various entities can deal
      with them. While the largest attacks affect all players (see,
      for instance, the Dyn attacks in October 2016), it is also true
      that large cloud- and content delivery providers can better deal
      with such attacks due to their scale. This is one reason among
      many that drives many network services to such
      providers. Another reason is the drive towards lower latency
      services, which can be best provided through globally
      distributed data centers.</t>

      <t>As technologists, one question we have is whether there are
      changes in technology that would help reduce technically-driven
      large-player advantages. This would lead to lower barriers to
      entry, more entities able to provide any particular service on
      the Internet, less dependence on a few players, and more choices
      and greater resilience for the network as a whole. </t>

      <t>Of course, it may well be that technology improvements are hard to
      come by. For instance:<list style="symbols">

      <t>Providing distributed, low-delay services seems like
      something that naturally fits larger entities better than
      small.</t>

      <t>Some technical issues may appear more suited for
      improvements, but have historically not been easy to solve, such
      as spam. Today, it is becoming increasingly difficult to run
      your own mail services, essentially forcing many organisations
      and individuals to employ larger providers. The issues relate
      directly to size of entities; no one can afford to disconnect
      from the largest providers. But as a small entity, there is
      little leverage to convince peer entities or various supporting
      white/blacklist entities to deal with you properly.</t>

      </list></t>

      <t>Nevertheless, recognising the risks of consolidation in both
      current and proposed future technologies is the first step in
      proactively avoiding those risks where possible.</t>

      <t>One avenue where further IETF work would be beneficial is
      better support for federation, which would enable entities (be
      they large or small) to work together to provide global
      services.</t>

      <t>Another big question is whether there are assumptions about
      the Internet architecture that no longer hold in a world where
      larger, more centralised entities provide big parts of the
      Internet service? If the world changes, the Internet and its
      technology/architecture may have to match those changes.</t>

      <t>One example of this is that more and more content is becoming
      available locally, from a content delivery or provider function
      directly on your own ISP's network. This trend seems strong, and
      eventually most of the content will be delivered this way,
      reducing the role that global IP connections across the Internet
      play. By some metrics this has already happened; what practical
      - positive or negative - impacts might this have on the Internet
      technology?</t>

      <t>Changes in business landscape may also affect standards work
      and processes. Small sets of significant players can drive
      standards work faster, but at the same time the larger entities
      are not as dependent on standardised solutions as smaller ones
      would be.</t>

      <t>What research on this topic should be driven forward? What
      IETF topics that should be pursued to address some of these
      questions?<list style="empty">

      <t>Note: If you are interested on this or other
      architecture-related topics, please subscribe to the IAB
      architecture-discuss mailing list as one forum for
      discussion.</t></list></t>

    </section>

    <section title="Consolidation">
      <t>Of course there are many different areas where consolidation
      might occur. For example, provision of content and services is
      observed to concentrate in the hands of a few entities;
      likewise, ISP services often achieve better efficiency at
      scale. Even operating systems, Web browsers and other tools
      experience this kind of tension, with too many or too few
      choices creating different kinds of problems. We all probably
      recognise at least some forms of these trends. In general, an
      efficient market such as the Internet tends to enable winners to
      take large market shares.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Choke Points">
    </section>

    <section title="Factors Leading to Consolidation">
    </section>
    
    <section title="Architectural Considerations of Consolidation">
    </section>
    
    <section title="Call for New Work">
      <section title="Understanding Assumptions about the Internet">
      </section>
      <section title="Technology to Alleviate Advantages of Large-Scale Players">
      </section>
      <section title="Research on State of the Internet">
      </section>
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="ack" title="Acknowledgements">

      <t>The authors would like to thank other IAB members
      and many others for interesting
      discussions in this problem space.</t>

    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>

    <references title="Informative References">

      &RFC1958;

    </references>

  </back>
</rfc>
